I'm home.
我回来了
Welcome back.
你回来啦
Welcome home.
欢迎回来
Wait. What are you doing, Urara?
等等 小丽 你在做什么？
I...
我…
I'm Mita, the housekeeper.
我是家政妇三田
What? What are you talking about?
什么？你在说什么？
Urara is here.
小丽来了
What?
什么？
Yui. Sorry but can I stay here?
小结 不好意思 我可以住这里吗？
Huh? What are you doing, Mita?
什么？三田小姐 你在做什么？
Dad chased me out of the house...
爸把我从家里赶出来了
Sorry.
抱歉
Seriously, what are you doing?
你在搞什么啊？
Nothing good happens when you're here, Urara.
小丽 你来的时候总是没好事
What are you guys talking about?
你们在说什么啊？
This is Mita, and this is Urara. Right?
这个是三田小姐 这个是小丽 对吧？
Yui!
姐姐
You know...
你知道…
You're dreaming right now, Yui.
你现在正在做梦吧？
You're Mita, right?
你是三田小姐 对吧？
Urara is here.
小丽小姐来了
What?
什么？
Yui. Sorry but can I stay here?
小结 不好意思 我可以住这里吗？
Dad chased me out of the house...
爸把我从家里赶出来了
Sorry.
抱歉
I'll clean it up.
我来处理吧
No way.
不会吧？
What are you saying, Yui?
姐 你在说什么啊？
Well, it's exactly the same as my dream. No, I mean it's the opposite.
跟我的梦一样 不对 完全相反
Are you sleep-talking right now?
你在说梦话吗？
I'm home.
我回来了
Welcome home.
你回来啦
I just came over, Keiichi.
我刚过来 姐夫
Oh, Urara. What's up?
是小丽啊 怎么了吗？
The other day when Dad got mad and said he doesn't care about the grandkids,
前几天爸生气了 说他才不在乎孙子们
we had a fight.
我们吵了一架
On top of that, he kept nagging me to go for blind dates.
而且他还一直唠叨 叫我去相亲
Hey. Could you say something to my dad?
姐夫你可以跟我爸说点什么吗？
Tell him that I don't intend on getting married.
告诉他我不打算结婚
But he probably won't listen to me.
但他可能不会听我的
He knows that I'm looking for a job right now.
他知道我现在在找工作
Daddy, you still can't find a job?
爸比 你还是找不到工作吗？
Well, it's quite difficult at times like this.
现在的时机要找工作很难
What does "times like this" mean?
“现在的时机”是什么意思？
What?
什么？
Well, we're in a recession right now.
我们现在经济不景气
What's a "recession"?
什么是“不景气”？
Well, that's...
这…
Mita, please help me.
三田小姐 请帮帮我
Recession refers to a period of time where business owners only want to earn money
不景气是指一段业主只想要赚钱
while bureaucrats only want to protect their own positions.
而官僚只想要保住职位的时期
And since the useless politicians are unable to do anything about it,
因为没用的政治人物无能
it causes a lot of people to lose their jobs and become poor.
让许多人失去工作 变得贫穷
Will you be fine, Dad?
爸 你不会有事吧？
Well... Don't worry too much.
别太担心
We'll be able to get by with my savings for now.
我们目前能靠我的存款过下去
And if you don't find a job soon, we won't be able to hire Mita anymore.
而且如果你不赶快找到工作 我们就请不起三田小姐了
Should I get a part-time job?
要不要我去打工？
I could deliver newspapers.
我可以去送报纸
I could also give up on applying for a private school, too.
我也可以放弃申请私立学校
I'll ask my friends in school!
我会问我学校的朋友
Maybe they know a good job!
也许他们知道什么好工作
Thanks, everyone. But I'll be fine.
谢谢大家 我不要紧的
Anyway, I'm hungry. Is dinner ready, Mita?
总之我饿了 三田小姐 晚餐准备好了吗？
It is done.
好了
Wow!
天啊
It looks delicious!
看起来好好吃喔
Why don't you join us, Urara?
小丽 你要不要加入我们？
Dad's right, Urara.
对啊 小丽
I think I should go home.
我想我该回家了
Don't say that. Why don't you eat here?
别这么说嘛 你在这里吃饭吧
I don't think it's right to freeload here when you're having a tough time.
我觉得你们都过得很辛苦了 我不能在这里白吃白喝
Besides. I can't sit on Nagiko's seat. See you!
而且我不能坐在姐的位子上 再见
Let's eat, shall we?
我们吃饭吧
-Thank you for the food. -I'm digging in.
-我开动了
I wonder if Urara has a place to stay.
不知道小丽有没有地方住
I don't think she has a boyfriend, either.
她也没有男朋友吧？
I thought about it, but...
我想过了 但…
Doesn't Urara like Dad?
小丽是不是喜欢爸？
What are you saying, Kaito?
小斗 你在说什么啊？
I mean, we may be relatives,
我是说 就算我们是亲戚吧
but isn't it strange of her to visit us so frequently?
但她这么常来看我们 是不是有点奇怪？
You're overthinking it.
你想太多了
That's not possible.
这是不可能的
Hey, Dad.
爸
Why don't we get Mita to join us?
要不要请三田小姐一起来吃？
Oh, you're right.
你说得对
Mita. Why don't you join us once in a while?
三田小姐 你偶尔跟我们一起吃吧
I'm fine.
我没关系
Don't say that.
别这么说嘛
We feel bad that you're always just looking at us eat.
你老是看着我们吃 让我们过意不去
Let's eat together, Mita.
一起吃吧 三田小姐
I...
我…
am just a housekeeper.
只是个家政妇
I will never eat with all of you.
我永远也不会和你们一起吃饭的
Mr. Asuda. The bath is ready.
主人 洗澡水准备好了
Oh, thanks.
好 谢谢
-I'm going in first. -Okay.
-我先去洗了 -好
Got it.
好
Hey. Why don't you play with us, Mita?
三田小姐 要不要跟我们一起玩？
Right, let's play together!
对啊 一起来玩吧
Is this an order?
这是命令吗？
Well, not exactly.
不算是
I'm sorry, but from now on,
很抱歉 但从现在起
please do not talk to me unless it's an order.
除非是命令 否则请别对我说话
Mita feels even colder than before.
三田小姐感觉比之前更冷漠了
Is it because we kept pressing her about her late family members?
是因为我们一直问她 过世的家人的事吗？
I believe I have said this before.
我相信我之前说过了
If you insist on questioning me, I will relieve myself of my duties.
如果你们执意追问 我就会辞职
What should we do, Yui?
姐姐 我们该怎么办？
Actually...
其实…
I thought about it, and...
我想过了 而且…
What?
什么？
I thought that Mita could be Mom's reincarnation.
我认为三田小姐可能是妈妈的化身
What in the world are you saying?
你在说什么啊？
She's right. Where's your evidence?
她说得对 你有证据吗？
I mean, Mita came to our house
三田小姐来我们家的时候
right after Mom's 49th day was over.
刚好是妈妈过世后49天
She even burned Mom's clothes and Buddhish altar nonchalantly.
她甚至还毫不在乎地 烧了妈妈的衣服和佛坛
Doesn't it make sense?
这不是很合理吗？
You guys surprised me! What is it?
吓我一跳 什么事？
We bought some monaka, Yui.
姐 我们带了一些最中饼来
So what? Just let me sleep in. It's a Saturday!
那又怎样？ 让我睡晚一点嘛 今天是周六
We want to check if Mita's a ghost.
我们想确认看看三田小姐是不是鬼
What?
什么？
If she eats this, it means she's a human.
如果她吃了这个 那就表示她是人类
Why don't you guys give it a rest already?
你们就忘了这件事吧
Then you don't care about Mita's real identity anymore?
那你不在乎 三田小姐真正的身份了吗？
That's not true, but...
也不是这样啦
Mita. Would you like to have a monaka?
三田小姐 你想吃最中饼吗？
Ms. Harumi from the agency said you like this, right?
介绍所的晴海女士 说你喜欢吃这个 对吧？
Not really. That's not true.
不对 并不是这样
What? Don't say that!
什么？别这么说嘛
Come on, have one!
来嘛 吃一个吧
What would you like for lunch?
你们午餐想吃什么？
I want hamburg steak. With lots of onions.
我想吃汉堡排 加很多洋葱
What? I prefer omelette rice.
什么？我比较想吃蛋包饭
That hurt!
好痛
She might tear up if she cuts onions.
她切洋葱可能会流眼泪
I see!
我懂了
Sorry! Let's have steaks instead!
抱歉 我们吃汉堡排吧
Understood.
我知道了
What do you need from me?
需要什么吗？
Oh, we're just wondering if you are going to tear up.
我们只是好奇你会不会流眼泪
Why so?
为什么好奇？
That's because...
因为…
Are you a ghost, Mita?
三田小姐 你是鬼吗？
Hey, Kii!
等等 希衣
Or are you Mom's reincarnation?
你是妈妈的化身吗？
I want to know more about you, Mita!
三田小姐 我想知道更多关于你的事
I believe I have told you
我相信我告诉过你们
not to talk to me unless it's an order.
除非是命令 否则不要对我说话
Then I have an order for you.
那我要向你下命令
What is it?
是什么？
Let's play scissors, paper, stone.
我们来猜拳
If I win, tell me more about yourself.
要是我赢了 你就要告诉我更多你的事
What if I win?
如果我赢了呢？
I promise that I'll never ask about you again!
我保证绝对不会再问起你的事
As you wish.
我知道了
I'm good at this game.
我很会猜拳
Let's go. Scissors, paper, stone!
开始吧 剪刀、石头、布
One more time! Scissors, paper, stone!
再一次 剪刀、石头、布
One last time! Scissors, paper, stone!
最后一次 剪刀、石头、布
Scissors, paper, stone!
剪刀、石头、布
No way!
讨厌
Well,
那…
why don't you have a duel with me?
你要不要跟我单挑？
We'll play with this.
我们玩这个
I'm done.
好了
Wow. Fifty-seven seconds.
天啊 57秒
Wow.
天啊
You're awesome, Kai!
你好厉害喔 小斗
Sorry, but I've never lost at this.
不好意思 我玩这个从来不输的
Here you go.
换你了
All right. Get ready.
好 准备好
Ready, go!
预备 开始
Five seconds.
五秒
The person who scores three points first wins.
先得三分的人就赢
Understood.
我知道了
You can go first. Here you go.
你可以先开始 来
No way.
不会吧
Kakeru!
小翔
That was just a fluke!
那只是侥幸
I'll score one this time!
我这次会得分的
I won't be careless anymore!
我不会再大意了
No way this is happening!
怎么可能？
It hurts!
好痛…
Please be more gentle!
请轻一点
Seriously, what were you doing? You're so lame.
说真的 你到底在干吗？你超逊的
Shut up.
闭嘴啦
I will now prepare dinner.
我现在去准备晚餐
Hey. What do you think is in that bag?
你们觉得那个包包里有什么？
Maybe it contains some hints.
也许里面有一些线索
Why don't the two of you stop it?
你们两个适可而止吧
He's right. You want to know who Mita really is, right?
他说得对 你想知道三田小姐 到底是什么人 对吧？
Personally...
我觉得…
I think maybe...
也许…
Mita might be like Urara.
三田小姐像小丽一样
What?
什么？
That's impossible.
不可能的
Yui. What is your evidence?
姐 你有证据吗？
Well, I had a similar dream.
我做了一个这样的梦
What's that?
什么梦？
I'm home.
我回来了
Welcome home.
欢迎回来
-Welcome home.
-你回来啦
How is it going with work, Dad?
爸 工作的事怎么样了？
Are you still in a "recession"?
还在“不景气”吗？
Well, yes.
是啊
-Sit, Dad. -What is it?
-坐吧 爸 -怎么了？
Help us, Dad.
帮帮我们 爸
Please! You're the only one who can help us now!
拜托 现在只有你能帮我们了
Okay. Can you just talk to Mita?
是这样的 你可以跟三田小姐聊天吗？
We'll take that chance to look through her bag.
我们趁机看她的包包
Hey. I don't think we should pry further.
我觉得我们不该再追究了
What will you do if she really quits?
万一她真的辞职了怎么办？
Please, Daddy!
拜托嘛 爸比
Excuse me, Mita.
不好意思 三田小姐
Yes?
什么事？
One of the lightbulbs in my room went out. Could you take a look?
我房间里有个灯泡不亮了 你可以去看看吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
-I can't open it! -What?
-我打不开 -什么？
-Hurry up. -What are you doing?
-快一点 -你们在做什么啊？
-Can someone bring me a screwdriver? -A screwdriver?
-可以拿螺丝刀来吗？ -螺丝刀
I just need a little more time!
我还需要一点时间
-Dad! -What?
-爸！ -什么？
I'm sorry,
不好意思
but could you not look at someone else's belongings without permission?
你们可以不要擅自看别人的东西吗？
Oh, sorry.
对不起
Besides...
而且…
Isn't there something else all of you should be doing?
你们没有别的事要做吗？
What?
什么？
What do you mean?
什么意思？
This is the Asuda residence.
这是阿须田家
Urara is on the phone, Mr. Asuda.
主人 是小丽小姐的电话
Oh, thanks.
谢谢
Hello? What's up, Urara?
喂？小丽 有什么事吗？
Sorry, Keiichi! But something happened to Dad.
抱歉 姐夫 爸出事了
What?
什么？
Sorry, everyone.
大家 对不起
What happened to father-in-law?
爸怎么了？
He got mad at some students who were smoking in front of the convenience store,
他对在便利商店前 抽烟的几个学生发脾气
and he got beat up instead.
结果被打了一顿
Dad.
爸
Keiichi and the kids are here.
姐夫和孩子们来了
I have nothing to say to them!
我对他们无话可说
What are you saying?
你在说什么啊？
Excuse me... Are you all right, father-in-law?
不好意思 爸 你还好吗？
Don't push yourself. We'll get worried.
不要太勉强自己 我们会担心的
I didn't ask you guys to be worried about me!
我可没叫你们担心我
Shut up!
闭嘴
It hurts...
好痛
Hurry up and go on a blind date, and give me a grandchild!
快点去相亲 帮我生个孙子
A well-behaved grandchild, unlike these kids over here!
生个乖孙子 不像这几个小孩一样
Stop raising your voice in the hospital!
不要在医院里这么大声
I'm not raising my voice at you!
我又不是在对你大声
Sorry about this even though you guys came.
对不起 你们都赶过来了
No, it's fine.
没关系的
Kii. Why don't you show Grandpa the stones?
希衣 你要不要给外公看石头？
Okay.
好
Grandpa.
外公
These stones represent our family.
这些石头代表我们家
This one's me, this one's Kai,
这是我 这是小斗
this one's Kakeru, this is Yui, this one's Mommy,
这是小翔 这是姐姐 这是妈妈
and Daddy put his stone in recently!
爸比最近把他的石头放进来了
Next time, I'll find yours and Urara's stone
下次我会找到你和小丽的石头
and put it in together.
然后放在一起
Your mother's no longer here!
你妈妈已经不在了
Stop holding on to these useless things!
不要再拿着这些没用的东西了！
-Dad! -What are you doing?
-爸！ -你在做什么？
You didn't have to vent it out on Kii.
别发泄在希衣身上啊
It's all your fault!
都是你的错
If only you died and Nagiko was alive,
要是你死了 而凪子还活着
things wouldn't have turned out like this!
情况就不会变成这样！
Seems like you managed to deceive them.
看来你想办法骗了他们
But it won't work on me!
但对我来说没用的
What do you think we should do?
你觉得我们该怎么办？
Mom...
妈
Mita.
三田小姐
I'll help you.
我来帮你吧
I'm fine. This is my job.
我来就好 这是我的工作
I want to help you. Please.
我想帮忙 拜托
As you wish.
我知道了
I used to help Mom with the chores at times.
以前我偶尔会帮妈做家事
Strangely enough,
说也奇怪
we could be honest with one another at times like this.
我们在这种时候能向彼此坦白
Hey.
对了
When you said there's something we should be doing...
当你说有件事我们该做时
You were referring to Grandpa, right?
你是指外公 对吧？
What should we do?
我们该怎么办？
Kakeru and Kaito said we should just leave him be.
小翔和小斗说应该别管他
Kii's totally afraid of Grandpa now, too.
现在希衣也很怕外公
Why does Grandpa always raise his voice? Was he always like that in the past?
为什么外公总是那么凶？ 他以前一直都这样吗？
Oh, sorry. I honestly thought I was talking to Mom just now.
抱歉 我以为我在跟妈妈说话
What do you need from me?
你需要什么吗？
What?
什么？
You're still staying with this family?
你还待在这个家啊？
Just when will you quit?
你什么时候才要辞职？
I don't think that's your business, Ms. Minagawa.
皆川阿姨 这不关你的事吧？
It seems like your father returned, too.
看来你爸爸也回来了
I'm surprised you allowed him to.
我很惊讶你们让他回来
He had an affair
他有外遇
and made your mother commit suicide.
还害你妈妈自杀
Are you sure you have the time
你确定你现在
to be saying things like this right now?
有空说这些话吗？
Huh? What do you mean?
什么意思？
Your husband was talking secretly on the phone the other day.
你先生前几天偷偷在打电话
"My wife hasn't realized at all, so it'll be fine.
“我太太完全没发现 没关系的
I'll separate from her soon enough." That was what he said.
我很快就会和她分开了” 他是这么说的
That's none of your business!
这不关你的事
All right!
好耶！
One more round.
再玩一回合
Wow, you're amazing.
你好厉害喔
Try a cat next, Mita.
三田小姐 接下来试试看猫叫
Everyone! Mita can imitate anything!
你们听我说 三田小姐什么都能模仿耶
Even the lady next door, too!
就连隔壁的阿姨也是
No way! Try it.
不会吧 试试看
"You're still staying with this family?"
“你还待在这个家啊？”
Wow, she's good!
她好厉害
Then can you imitate someone from AKB48?
那你可以模仿AKB48的成员吗？
I can do all of them.
全部都可以
You can imitate all of them?
你能模仿全部的成员？
Then let's start from the first place girl.
那先从第一名的女生开始
No, the one from the Rock, Paper, Scissors Tournament.
不要 从选拔猜拳大会的开始
Mita!
三田小姐
I have a request.
我有一个要求
We came to a nearby park for a picnic today.
我们今天来附近的公园野餐
You should smile wider, Mom.
你应该笑得更灿烂一点 妈
Stop this, it's embarrassing.
好了 这样很难为情
-Do it, Mom! -No way.
-笑嘛 妈 -不要啦
-Okay. Ready, go. -I'm digging in.
-好 开始了 -我开动了
Mita. Could you imitate Mom?
三田小姐 你能模仿妈吗？
I can.
能
Then could you go to the hospital and pretend to be Mom's ghost?
那可以请你去医院 假装是妈妈的鬼魂吗？
What are you talking about, Yui?
姐 你在说什么啊？
If she conveys our feelings using Mom's voice,
要是她能用妈的声音传达我们的心情
Grandpa might be willing to accept it.
外公或许能接受
That's not going to work. It's all over once he sees Mita's face.
这不会成功的 他一看到三田小姐的脸就完了
It's going to be fine.
不会有事的
If we turn off the lights, it will be dark and he can't see her face.
如果把灯关掉 就会很暗 他就看不到三田小姐的脸了
Please, Mita! I want to make up with Grandpa somehow.
拜托你 三田小姐 我要想办法跟外公和好
Is that an order?
这是命令吗？
Yes.
对
As you wish.
我知道了
Dad.
爸
Who's there?
是谁？
Dad. How's your body?
爸 你身体还好吗？
Is that you, Nagiko?
凪子 是你吗？
I'm sorry that I died before you, Dad.
对不起 我比你先走了 爸
Nagiko!
凪子
That hurt...
好痛
I...
我…
When Keiichi told me to divorce him,
当惠一要我和他离婚时
I thought about how all the efforts I put in into my marriage life
我想到我对婚姻投注了那么多努力
went down the drain,
全都付诸流水
and I felt like I had no reason to live anymore.
我觉得自己没有理由再活下去了
But now...
但是现在…
I regret that I left the kids.
我后悔我丢下了孩子们
Even if he had left me,
就算他离开我
I should have taken care of the children.
我也应该照顾孩子的 所以…
Why does it seem like she's not following the script?
为什么她好像没有照剧本走呢？
Could you protect Yui and the kids in my place?
你能代替我照顾小结他们吗？
I understand that you hate Keiichi,
我明白你恨惠一
but please forgive him for the children's sake.
但是请为了孩子们原谅他
Please.
拜托
I'm scared, Nagiko.
我好怕 凪子
Yui told me, too.
小结对我说过
She said that all the people important to me become unhappy.
她说对我重要的人都会变得不快乐
You and your mother...
你和你妈…
And Urara. Being with me may make you all unhappy.
还有小丽 和我在一起 可能让你们都变得不快乐
And that thought made me so scared.
这个想法让我很害怕
If I'm going to be haunted by these thoughts, I think it'll be better
如果我要被这些想法纠缠
if I was dead first.
那我先死了也好
Why did you die?
你为什么要死？
Why did you and your mother die?
为什么你和你妈要死？
Hey, what are you guys doing?
你们在做什么？
-What? -Hey, what's going on?
-什么？ -怎么了？
Mita told me that she came to the hospital.
三田小姐告诉我她来医院
Why don't we just go in?
直接进去吧
What the hell are you doing here?
你在这里做什么？
There's a limit to your jokes!
开玩笑也要有个限度
What are you doing, Dad?
爸 你做什么啊？
Don't blame Mita, Grandpa!
不要怪三田小姐 外公
I was the one who asked her to pretend to be Mom.
是我要求她假装成妈妈的
What did you say?
你说什么？
How dare you come up with such a prank. You think it's funny?
你竟敢想出这种恶作剧 觉得这样很好玩吗？
I'm sorry.
对不起
I never want to see your face again. Get out!
我再也不想看到你的脸 滚出去
You didn't have to take it that far, Dad.
你也不用这样吧 爸
I'm sorry, father-in-law. I apologize in their place.
爸 对不起 我代替他们道歉
Hey, Dad!
等等 爸
Just leave me alone already!
不要来烦我
Visiting hours are already over.
探访时间已经结束了
Oh, I'm sorry.
对不起
Everyone. Let's go home for today, okay?
大家 我们今天就先回家 好吗？
Please excuse us.
失陪了
Let's go. Hurry.
快走吧
Mita?
三田小姐？
Let's go home.
回家吧
What are you looking at?
你在看什么？
Get out!
出去
It's a lie.
那是谎言
What?
什么？
The fact that everyone important to you becomes unhappy
对你重要的人都变得不快乐
is all a lie.
这全是谎言
What did you say?
你说什么？
You simply tried to love your family
你只是试着用自己的方式
using your own method.
去爱你的家人
You raise your voice
你老是很凶
because your feelings don't reach them
是因为你的感受无法传达
and you feel frustrated by that.
这让你觉得挫折
In truth, you don't have confidence
事实上你没有自信
and you're scared that it will be exposed.
你害怕这一点会被暴露出来
You are just...
你只是…
raising your voice at yourself.
在对自己大骂
Shut up!
闭嘴
What would a housekeeper like you know?
像你这样的家政妇懂什么？
I understand the pain of losing people important to you.
我懂失去重要的人的痛苦
I understand that empty feeling of not being able to be with them again.
我懂再也无法与他们在一起的空虚感
However, you still have...
然而你仍然有机会
the chance to give happiness to the ones you love.
为你爱的人带来快乐
Grandpa.
外公
I found it.
我找到了
I found Grandpa and Urara's stones.
我找到外公跟小丽的石头了
Urara.
小丽
Will you two place them into this box?
可以请你放进这个盒子里吗？
This is yours, Urara.
这是你的 小丽
Thanks.
谢谢
This is yours, Grandpa.
这是你的 外公
Dad.
爸
Yui and the kids
小结他们
want you to get better.
想要你快点好起来
They want to do everything they can to make up with you.
他们尽全力要跟你和好
I'll come visit you everyday until you're discharged, Grandpa.
我会每天都来看你的 外公 直到你出院为止
Me too. The entrance exams are coming,
我也是 入学考试就快到了
so you have to help me with revision.
所以你要帮我复习
Grandpa.
外公
We're a family.
我们是一家人
We're your family, Grandpa. Are we not?
外公 我们是一家人 对不对？
Here you go.
来
ASUDA RESIDENCE
（阿须田家）
Don't make that face, Dad!
不要那个表情嘛 爸
Keiichi and the kids are going to take it the wrong way again.
姐夫跟孩子们又要误会了
Shut up! I'm born with this face.
闭嘴 我天生就是这个脸
I got it! It sounds like you're raising your voice since you tend to talk loudly.
我懂了 你常常说话很大声 所以听起来像是凶巴巴的
Right. Why don't you end your sentences in a cute manner?
你要不要用可爱的方式 将句子做结尾？
What do you mean?
什么意思？
Don't say "Shut up!", but "Shut up, as it were!"
不要说“闭嘴” 而是说“闭嘴喔”
See? It's cute!
这样是不是很可爱？
Are you dumb? There's no way I'd say that!
笨蛋 我不可能那么说的
Just try it once.
试一次嘛
"Shut up, as it were!"
“闭嘴喔”
Shut up! Just press the doorbell already!
闭嘴 按门铃就是了
Jeez...
真是的
Nagiko. Dad's finally discharged from the hospital.
姐 爸终于出院了
Thanks, Nagiko.
谢谢你 凪子
Father-in-law.
爸
I'm sorry that you had to buy a Buddhist altar for us.
对不起 还让你为我们买佛坛
That can't be helped.
这也是没办法的事
I can't let an unemployed man fork out money!
我不能让一个没工作的人掏钱出来
Hey, Dad!
喂 爸
The children...
孩子们…
They are finally ready to accept their mother's death.
他们终于准备好接受妈妈的死了
This morning, they prayed to her before leaving for school.
今天早上他们去上学前向她祭拜了
Right now...
现在…
They are truly growing up by the day.
他们真的天天都在长大
Father-in-law.
爸
I'm sorry.
对不起
Keiichi...
姐夫
It's my fault that
都是我的错
you weren't able to give your beloved daughter happiness.
让你无法为亲爱的女儿带来幸福
I let her die before you.
我让她比你先走
Nagiko looked forward to
凪子是最期待
the children growing up, more than anyone else.
看到孩子们成长的
I'm truly sorry....
我真的很抱歉…
that she couldn't do so.
让她无法这么做
Keiichi, I planned a party for Dad's discharge tomorrow.
姐夫 明天我为爸出院 安排了一场宴会
Okay, I got it. I'll let the children know.
好 我知道了 我会让孩子们知道
Okay.
好
Right. Can Mita join us?
对了 三田小姐可以加入吗？
I'm sure the kids will be happy, too.
相信这样孩子们也会开心的
Yes, of course.
好啊 当然可以
You're okay with it, right Mita?
三田小姐 你可以吧？
I will not be going.
我不会去
Please don't say that.
请别这么说
It's been a while since the family gathered.
全家人有好一阵子没有聚在一起了
I am not part of the family.
我不是这家庭的一分子
Dad?
爸？
I'm sorry about
对不起
my harsh actions to you the other day...
那天我对你那么严厉
as it were.
…喔
I really think...
我真的认为…
I really think that you're a good person, as it were.
我真的认为你是好人…喔
I want you to come tomorrow, as it were!
我希望你明天来…喔
HARUMI HOUSEKEEPING AGENCY
（晴海家政妇介绍所）
This is the referral commission for this month.
这是这个月的介绍费
Received with thanks.
收到了 谢谢
Please excuse me.
失陪了
Hey, I heard about the party from the kids.
我听孩子们说了宴会的事
What are you going to do?
你要怎么做？
Hey, this is not stipulated in the regulations.
规定上没有明确要求
Don't be such a stiff and say that you're not attending
不要这么冷漠 说你不参加
since housekeepers are not part of the family.
是因为家政妇不是家庭的一分子嘛
Akari.
灯子
Do you remember the first time I gave you a monaka?
还记得我第一次 给你最中饼的时候吗？
I think you were this small.
我想你那时还这么小
Right? You hid your loneliness every single day,
对吧？你每天都藏着自己的寂寞
and smiled as much as you could.
而且努力露出笑容
And I became so old in a blink of the eye.
我一下子就变得这么老了
So, I want to see your smile once more before I die.
我死前想再看一次你的笑容
Haven't you done enough?
你做得还不够吗？
It's time you believed in someone and opened your heart to them.
你也该信任别人 向别人敞开心胸了
Right?
对吧？
I think that family is wonderful.
我认为那家人很棒
OGURA MONAKA
（小仓最中饼）
When the long winter finally ends and spring comes...
当漫长的冬天终于结束 春天来临时
even ice would melt.
就连冰也会融化的
Welcome.
欢迎
-Welcome.
-欢迎
Excuse me, we have a reservation under the name "Yuki".
你好 我们用“结城”这名字预约了
Please give me a moment.
请稍等
It's really hard to get a reservation here.
这里很难预约耶
Wow. Urara really tried her best.
小丽真的很努力耶
Sorry to keep you waiting.
抱歉久等了
We indeed have a reservation under that name for eight people,
这个名字的确预约了八人
but it is supposed to be on the same date next month.
但应该是下个月的同一天
What?
什么？
Wait. Then what about today?
等等 那今天呢？
I'm sorry, but we're fully booked today.
抱歉 我们今天预约已经满了
What the hell?
什么啊？
I can't connect to Urara's phone right now.
现在小丽的电话打不通
What? Then what should we do?
什么？那我们该怎么办？
Jeez, you can count on Urara to mess things up.
天啊 小丽总是会搞砸
Just what are you doing? It's almost time to leave.
你在做什么？差不多要出发了
Give me a minute. I lost the printed map for the restaurant,
等我一下 我把印出来的餐厅地图弄丢了
so I have no idea where it is.
我不知道餐厅在哪里
If we don't hurry, the others are going to reach first.
要是不赶快 其他人会先到的
Oh, no!
糟糕
What?
怎么了？
The computer froze.
电脑卡住了
I can't believe you.
你也真是的
You better give them a call.
你最好打给他们
I know!
我知道
I left my phone at school.
我把电话忘在学校了
Just use the home phone.
-用家里的电话 -我知道
I don't know their number without my phone.
没有我的手机 我不知道他们的电话
Just what are you doing, as it were?
你到底在做什么呀？
You still can't reach Urara?
还是联络不上小丽吗？
Yes.
对
Just what is she doing?
她在做什么啊？
Man... I'm so hungry that I'm going to die!
我快饿死了
I'll cook something now.
我立刻煮点东西
Mita.
三田小姐
Why don't we order sushi for today?
今天我们叫寿司吧？
Oh, right! Join us, Mita.
对啊 一起吃吧 三田小姐
No, I'm fine.
不用了 我没关系
Please!
拜托你
This is a good chance.
这是个好机会
Let's have a proper talk.
我们好好谈谈吧
When I heard what you told Grandpa,
当我听到你对外公说的话
it really felt as if Mom was there.
真的觉得好像是妈妈在场
I thought that you might really be Mom's reincarnation.
我想你可能真的是妈妈的化身
I...
我…
I am not your mother.
我不是你们的妈妈
Then tell us about yourself!
那告诉我们你的事
You told Grandpa, didn't you?
你不是对外公说了吗？
That you understand the pain of losing people important to you,
你明白失去重要的人的痛苦
as well as the empty feeling of not being able to be with them again.
还有不能再和他们在一起的空虚感
Please.
拜托
I...
我…
I want to protect you!
我想保护你
Mita...
三田小姐
Could you eat with the kids today?
今天和孩子们一起吃饭 好吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
Yay!
太好了
Sit here, Mita.
三田小姐 来坐这里
All right!
好耶
Right. I'll go order sushi.
对了 我去订寿司
Oh, right!
对了
Why don't we have monaka while we wait for the sushi?
等寿司的时候来吃最中饼吧
Right. I'm so hungry that I can't take it anymore.
好 我饿到受不了了
It looks pretty unassuming,
看起来平凡无奇
but it's delicious with all the bed bean paste.
但是里面的红豆馅让它很好吃
It sounds just like Mita.
听起来像三田小姐一样
I'm beginning to like monaka!
我开始喜欢上最中饼了
Oh. Maybe I'll have one, too.
那我也来吃一个吧
Have one too, Mita.
你也吃一个吧 三田小姐
Have one.
吃一个
All right!
好耶
-Just how many are you going to eat? -Here you go, Kii.
-你要吃几个啊？ -来 希衣
Good, isn't it? Don't eat too much though.
很好吃 对吧？不过别吃太多了
You're having sushi after this.
等一下还有寿司
I received a monaka...
我第一次拿到最中饼
for the first time from the president of the housekeeping agency
是家政妇介绍所所长给我的
when I was around Kii's age.
当时我和希衣年纪差不多
One year before that,
在那之前一年
my beloved father tried to save me from drowning in a nearby river,
我在附近的河里差点溺水 我亲爱的父亲试着救我
and he died instead.
结果他死了
Ever since then, my mother harbored resentment in her heart
从此以后 我母亲对我心怀怨恨
towards me for killing her dear husband,
认为我害死了她心爱的丈夫
and started to avoid me.
开始避着我
I did my best in my studies and other activities
我在学业和其他活动上尽全力表现
in an attempt to make her happy.
就为了让她开心
However, once she remarried and gave birth to her child,
然而在她再婚生子之后
all she cared about was my younger brother.
她只在乎我的弟弟
When my stepfather made eyes at me,
当我继父开始对我有意思时
my mother grew to hate me even more.
我母亲变得更恨我了
"It's all because of your smile."
“都是因为你的笑容
"Your smile brings misfortune to everyone around you."
你的笑容会给你身边 所有人带来不幸”
She always reprimanded me.
她总是责怪我
However, Ms. Harumi, who was my housekeeper at that time,
然而当时在我家 担任家政妇的晴海女士
cheered me on and I tried to smile as much as I could.
为我加油 我努力露出笑容
I believed that I would meet someone who would accept me
我相信我有一天会遇见一个人
for who I am one day.
能接受本来的我
And then, I met my husband.
然后我遇见了我丈夫
I gave birth to a boy who looked just like him.
我生下一个长得很像他的男孩
When I see the both of them eating and praising my cooking,
当我看见他们两人 吃我煮的东西 赞美我的厨艺时
I didn't need anything else in my life.
我人生中再也不需要别的东西
I was so happy every day,
我当时每天都好幸福
and I lived on as I smiled from the bottom of my heart.
在生活中发自内心露出笑容
One day,
有一天
my younger brother came to my house.
我弟弟来我家
He confessed his love to me, and started following me around.
他向我告白 并开始跟着我
My husband never knew what was his intention,
我丈夫完全不知道他的意图
and welcomed him to our house all the time.
总是欢迎他来我们家
My brother used the opportunity
我弟弟利用这个机会
to force me to further advance our relationship,
强迫我和他进一步发展关系
and started to stalk me.
开始跟踪骚扰我
While we have different fathers,
虽然我们父亲不同
we are still blood-related siblings.
仍然是有血缘的手足
So,
所以
I rejected his advances numerous times.
我多次拒绝他的求爱
I told him, "Please stop this" over and over again.
我一再告诉他“请停止”
But it didn't work.
但没有用
Eventually, my husband found out about my brother's real intention.
最后我丈夫发现了我弟弟真正的意图
My husband told him, "Never come back here again."
我丈夫告诉他“永远不要再回来”
and my brother flew into a rage.
我弟弟大发雷霆
He said, "It's your fault. You seduced me."
他说“这是你的错 是你引诱我的”
And he set our house on fire.
然后他放火烧我们的家
As the flames grew bigger,
随着火势越来越大
I could hear someone shout, "Save me, Mom! Save me!"
我能听到有人大喊 “救我 妈妈 救我”
It was my son screaming.
那是我儿子在大喊
I tried to run into the fire.
我试着跑进火里
However...
然而…
The firefighters stopped me.
消防员阻止了我
My beloved husband and son...
我心爱的丈夫和儿子…
They died.
死了
And as if he were trying to mock me,
接着 仿佛是要嘲笑我一般
my younger brother killed himself.
我弟弟自杀了
My mother and my husband's parents told me...
我妈妈和我的公公婆婆告诉我
"It's your fault. That smile of yours always brings misfortune to everyone."
“都是你的错 你的笑容总是带给大家不幸”
"Enough with the apologies."
“不要再道歉了”
"You don't have to do anything."
“你什么也不用做”
"Just don't smile until you die."
“到死前都不要笑就好了”
And with that, everything's gone from my life.
就这样 我人生中的一切都没了
Light, hopes, dreams, love...
光明、希望、梦想、爱
joy, happiness,
喜悦、幸福
and future. All of them disappeared.
还有未来都没了
I talked about everything regarding myself.
我说出了关于我的一切
As promised...
依照承诺
I will now quit my job.
我现在就辞职
Wait. Mita, please wait!
等等 三田小姐 等一下
MITA MOVES TO A NEW STAGE 15-MINUTES EXTENDED EPISODE
（三田进入新阶段 下集加长15分钟）
Don't get in my way!
请不要阻碍我
All of you will die if you don't.
否则你们也会没命
I do not deserve to have a will of my own.
我不该拥有自己的意志
I've been waiting
我一直在等待
for this day to come.
这一天的到来
I know that the sadness you feel
我知道你经历的痛苦与悲伤
is nothing comparable to ours.
与我们无法相比
This time,
这一次
we want to save you, Mita!
我们想让你获得救赎 三田小姐
Do you like me, Mita?
三田小姐 你喜欢我吗？
I don't ever want to let go of our bond!
我绝不想失去我们之间的羁绊
I won't let go, even if I die!
就算失去性命 我也不会放手
Subtitle translation by: Qianni Lu
字幕翻译：吴敬美